Guide to the Graduate Students Union Records, 2013-2018 UA.31.10.0005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Graduate Students Union Records
2013-2018 (bulk 2016-2017)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Graduate Students Union
UA.31.10.0005
2 Gigabytes
.1 Linear Feet
The Duke Graduate Students Union is a student organization partnered with the Service Employees International Union (SEIU) to create a labor union representing graduate student workers at Duke University. Records cover the campaign to form a collective bargaining union as well as subsequent efforts to organize as a direct-action, direct-join union.
Biographical / Historical
The Duke Graduate Students Union (DGSU) formed in early 2016, when graduate student workers partnered with the Service Employees International Union (SEIU). These two organizations campaigned to form a majority union and petitioned the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB). The election in March 2017 was inconclusive: although the tabulated votes indicated the vote would fail, enough ballots remained contested by SEIU and the University to tip the vote in either direction. SEIU, acting on behalf of DGSU, withdrew the petition to unionize from the NLRB. Since spring 2017, DGSU exists as a direct-action, direct-join union and is active on campus advocating for increased benefits for graduate student workers, as well as organizing alongside other employee labor groups at Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
Access copies of electronic records must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Duke Graduate Students Union records were received by the Duke University Archives as a transfer in 2017 and 2018.
Scope and Contents
The Duke Graduate Students Union records span 2013-2018, with the bulk of the material from 2016-2017. Records include correspondence with University administration, the Graduate and Professional Student Council (GPSC), DGSU membership, and University listserves, as well as solidarity letters from other labor entities. Also included are promotional materials such as presentations and advertisements, collected anti-union organizing materials, meeting notes, legal documents filed with the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) related to the petition to unionize, media coverage, and photographs of events held by DGSU during their campaign.
Labor movement; Labor unions -- North Carolina; Graduate students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. University Archives
- Administration Correspondence, 2016-2017; 13 document files (PDF format); approximately 6 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Advertisements, 2016; 1 document file (PDF format); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Anti-Union Organizing Efforts, 2016-2017; 11 document and image files (predominantly PDF format); approximately 5 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Continuation Fees, 2015 and undated; 3 document files (PDF and DOCX formats); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- E-mail Blasts, 2016-2017; 21 document files (PDF format); approximately 9 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Fliers and Other DGSU Publications, 2016-2017; 9 document and image files (predominately PDF format); approximately 6 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- GPSC Correspondence, 2016; 2 document files (PDF format); approximately 1 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Graduate Workers Forward pin (Folder 1)
- Intra-Department Listserves on Grad Union, 2016-2017; 17 document files (PDF and DOCX formats); approximately 9 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Media Coverage, 2016-2017; 38 document files (PDF format); approximately 23 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Meeting Notes (Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous, 2017; 2 document files (PDF format); approximately 3 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- NLRB Legal Documents, 2016-2017; 15 document files (PDF format); approximately 20 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Photos, 2016-2017 and undated; 531 still image and video files (predominantly JPEG and MPEG-4 formats); approximately 2 GB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Presentations, undated; 1 document file (PDF format); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Sample Grad Student Contracts and Work Assignment Letters, 2013-2016; 4 document files (PDF and DOCX formats); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Solidarity Letters, 2016-2017; 5 document files (predominantly PDF format); approximately 2 MB. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0005-SET-0001)
- Handwritten meeting notes, 2016 (Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Michael Becker's handwritten notes: "these notes are from a July 30, 2016 training on university endowments and financing sponsored by SEIU for Duke, UNC, and local community college adjunct faculty, graduate student workers and undergraduate labor solidarity activists. Presenters were from the whistleblowing / activist-research groups LittleSis and Hedge Clippers. This training was part of developing a deeper analysis of Duke's finances to make a case for the financial feasibility of the changes to graduate student funding, benefits, and other measures we were making and to develop messaging to our fellow graduate student workers."
- Union sign-up cards and mailings, circa 2016 (Folder 2)
- Flyer, Frequently Asked Questions, articles, agendas, and other materials, 2016 (Folder 2)
- Flyers, agendas, notes, pamphlets, and SEIU Southern Region membership packets, 2018 (Folder 3)